It is never too late to become a top student.
I used to struggle during my first year at university, and I used to accumulate bad grades, and now I'm a student at Oxford
University, and I recently received an award for my outstanding PhD work.
I am the perfect example that anyone can be an academic weapon if they want to.
So this video is going to be the ultimate guide on how to ditch your old mentality and become an overachiever in any aspect of academia.
I will cover five key areas: motivation, time management, note-taking, study methods, and exam prep.
So let's start with the key ingredient, motivation.
Your mindset is either the most important superpower that you will ever have or your biggest enemy.
Having a mindset where you don't believe in yourself, where you don't care about grades, and don't think about your future, that is the most detrimental to your
success.
In the end of the day, you are the person creating your future, and no one can do it for you.
You're the one who needs to push yourself, who needs to believe in yourself, because I promise you that anyone can be an academic weapon with the right
mindset and the right approaches.
Being a top student starts with motivation.
If you don't want to study, if you don't care about exams, you already lost.
Think to yourself, why are you taking this subject?
Why are you at this university or this school?
If your answer is that you don't want to let down your parents or you're afraid of the teacher, that is not a good reason.
Your drive needs to come within yourself.
And you can achieve this if you think about the big picture.
If you do well in school, your chances of getting into your dream university are much higher.
Your chances of studying the subject that you love are much more realistic.
You get to decide which career path you want to take, and you're currently building the foundational knowledge that is required to get where you want to be
in the future.
If you only sit down to study because someone else tells you to, you will never have the curiosity and drive that it takes to understand and soak
up all of the knowledge that is needed to perform well in school, in academia, and in your career.
If you don't know where to find that motivation or if you lack that motivation, I recommend sitting down and creating a vision board of
yourself, focusing on where you want to be and what you want to achieve in life.
It might help you to find the drive in yourself and to identify what exactly you need to do to get to where you want to
be, and identify why what you do now is important for your future self.
Next, let's talk about time management.
First tip I have is limit distractions.
Honestly, the older I get, the more I realize how valuable time is.
It is honestly like a currency, but a lot more valuable because you can't get it back.
We have about 16 hours a day where we can actually do stuff, which sounds like a lot, but if you're a productive person that gets a lot
of stuff done each day, it really isn't that much time.
Especially if you spend about two hours a day scrolling through social media, that is more than 12% of time lost every single day that you could have
used for something else.
And that is the big problem.
If you sit in a library to study and you just end up doom scrolling, you actually just waste your time whilst not getting done anything at all.
So my advice is to consciously think how you want to use your time.
A one hour session of active studying without any distraction is so much more valuable than sitting in the library for four hours, but actually just being on
your phone or chatting with friends.
Tip number two is to identify priorities.
This is especially true for university where we have endless books to read, and it can feel quite overwhelming not knowing where to start
and, more importantly, not knowing where to stop.
I myself used to start at chapter one and try to learn everything by heart, but then run out of time when it came to later
chapters, but not all of The information or resources that you are given by your teachers are actually important for your exams.
So instead of blindly starting and like trying to learn everything by heart in one go, you need to have a plan and identify what is actually important.
Usually, professors drop loads of little hints during the classes of the topics that are important and that will come up in your next exam.
And if you pay attention, you can then focus on especially these chapters when you do your study sessions.
It is a classic strategy of working smarter and not harder.
So I experienced an example of that.
When I did my German A-levels, our professors would focus on this one specific book for three months, and he would make sure that we discuss all of
the analogies, all of the metaphors.
So I was 99% sure that this will be the topic in my A-level exams.
And whilst most of my other classmates focused on poems because that's what they are more familiar with, I focused specifically on this book for my whole revisions.
And I was not surprised when I opened the exam paper and I saw a chapter of the book.
And that year, I was the only person scoring full points in this exam.
And in my teacher's career, there were only three people who ever achieved that, including me.
And that's not because I was smarter, but because I knew exactly what to study for.
So understanding which topics are likely to be covered in the exam is so important to wisely organize your study sessions.
Also, if you're taking A-levels or taking university exams, I really recommend searching up the internet or asking people in your year above what their experience was like
or what topics were covered in last year's exams.
Because that could always be a good indicator because often from year to year, there are certain trends of topics that are often covered in those exams.
This leads me to my next point, which is tip number three, organize your time wisely.
The easiest way to do this is to create a study plan and structure out what you're going to study when.
So a quick breakdown of how I do it is for each exam I have, I write down every single topic or subtopic that I need to be
confident in.
And then I organize this into my calendar so I know exactly what I want to achieve every single day.
Visualizing when you're going to do what is so helpful to identifying how much you can realistically achieve in the time frame you have, and it also removes
this big layer of feeling overwhelmed because you know exactly where to start and where you're going to be in the next days or weeks.
I actually plan out my whole week in one hour time blocks, and I did make a video about it, so if you're curious on how I structure
my weeks and plan my study sessions, I link it down in the description below.
Let's move on to note-taking.
First tip is to prepare my study materials as early as possible.
With any class that you take, even if your exam is months away, start preparing your study material as early as possible because now is the time when
it's fresh in your mind.
I actually only started doing this during my master's, and I wish I could go back in time and tell my younger self to start doing this because
after I applied this method, I got top grades in every single exam I had afterwards.
So what exactly did I actually do?
So every time I had a new lecture or I had some reading to do, I not only prepared my lecture notes or my reading
notes, but I also prepared flashcards and exam questions with the relevant answer.
That way, when it actually came to exam season, I had so much exam prep to already go through.
Before my master's, I used to start creating these materials literally like a month prior to an exam, and then it used to take me days if not
a week to put all of these materials together, so this strategy not only saved me so much time but also brain energy because I can now fully
focus on actually getting prepared for the exam because rather than rereading chapters and trying to identify which knowledge I Know and which knowledge I don't
know, I could instantly start testing myself on my knowledge that I have or don't have.
Moving on to study methods.
Don't pretend to study, but be honest with yourself and what you're actually doing.
I used to spend hours and hours in the library reading chapters of a book, highlighting and rewriting those things as a summary in my notebook.
If this sounds like you, I have to tell you, this is such a big waste of time.
And unless you have a photographic memory, it is very likely that you just won't remember any of what you've just read just a couple of hours later.
Honestly, put this to the test.
Read a paragraph of anything, and I bet you that literally in just an hour, you won't remember half of it.
And that is really detrimental for your exam because you feel like you've spent hours and hours in the library and you've put in so much
work, only to realize that once you sit in the exam room and you see those questions, that you don't actually understand the topic at all.
Reading, highlighting, and summarizing is just a form of passive learning.
It tricks your brain into thinking that you're being productive, but actually it's kind of like a vacation for your brain because you're not actually actively using
it, meaning that when the information enters your brain, you don't really utilize it, so it will be forgotten as quickly as it has entered your brain.
So instead, you need to use study methods that actively engage your brain, where you have to think about the information or answers to
questions, and where you test yourself, and where you identify, do you actually understand this topic?
Very efficient ways of active studying are flashcards, mock exams, explaining things to people, or you could even use ChatGBT.
So if you input all of your textbook information into ChatGBT and then ask it to curate exam questions, that's a really good way to identify if you
actually know the answers.
If you just read a text, you have the answer right in front of it, and it makes sense to you.
However, if you read a question, you actively have to engage your brain, and you have to think about the answer, and you have to formulate an answer
in your own words.
Honestly, you'll be surprised about how difficult it can be to formulate an answer if you're not super comfortable in a topic, but it is the best way
to hold yourself accountable on whether or not you're confident in the subject or not.
Will it be more tiring and energy draining?
Definitely, but it is a lot more effective, and you actually have to use a lot less time to study because it is just a lot more efficient.
So an hour of active learning is so much better than a five-hour session of just rereading information.
Tip number two is to ask questions.
Yes, I used to be that student that constantly raised their hand in class to ask questions.
And do I regret it?
Absolutely not.
If you go into a lesson thinking, I need to ask a question, it actually actively forces you to listen to the teacher and to try to understand
the topic.
You are not only less likely to zone out, but also it gives you the chance to talk about this topic actively with either your teacher or your
classmates.
Not only will it help you to remember specific things better, because when you sit in the exam, you can think back to this exact
moment, and it is likely that you will kind of remember what the answer to your question was when you ask it.
But also, by asking questions, you can ensure whether or not you actually just understood what the teacher told you.
And if you're generally a shy person, I'll let you in on a little secret.
Even if it seems like everyone in your class understands the topic because no one else is raising their hand, chances are they do not.
It is very likely that most of them either weren't listening at all, which to be honest is their loss, or they are too shy to ask as
well.
So usually people are rather relieved when someone else asks a question, because usually they did have a similar question.
Question as well.
So it doesn't only benefit you, but it also benefits people around you.
Okay, let's move on to exam prep.
Tip number one is to practice exam conditions.
Honestly, two exams could have completely different conditions, and you don't want to enter the exam room not knowing what to expect.
So, for example, when I was in high school, my math exam was made out of two sections.
The first one was like quick tasks where we weren't allowed to use a calculator, and we were supposed to do this relatively quickly.
And the second section were more complex questions where we were allowed to use a calculator.
And we were supposed to spend a lot more time on that section.
So if I hadn't done any practice exams with these conditions, I probably would have spent way too much time on the first section and then run out
of time in the second part of the exam.
So understanding how the exam will look like is honestly key.
Is your exam essay based?
If so, understand how the structure of an essay should look like.
Is your exam composed of multiple choice questions?
Then there's no point in trying to practice writing essays, but you should do multiple choice based mock exams.
Another thing to consider is whether your exam will be on your laptop or if you have to write it by hand.
I personally never write with my hand anymore, so if I know that my exam will be two hours long and it will be
handwritten, I will have to practice that, so I know that my hand is conditioned enough to be able to write for two hours straight.
So practicing the conditions of your exam will not only help you to manage your time wisely during your exam, but also now that you're familiar with how
everything is set up, it will help you a lot more to control your nerves when it comes to the exam, and you will feel a lot less
overwhelmed because you've done this before.
This is nothing new to you anymore.
And also, I wanted to give a little tips specifically for multiple choice questions.
So I did my A-levels in the German system, and we didn't have multiple choice really.
Like everything was essay based or short answer based.
So when I came to the UK, and professors here in the UK love multiple choice exams, I used to do terrible because to me the four given
answers just seemed so similar that I couldn't distinguish of which one is actually the most right one.
So I just wanted to give a very brief tips and tricks of what I figured out throughout the years of how to actually tackle these multiple choice
exams successfully.
Okay, the first one is instead of trying to look for the right answer, try to look for which answers are definitely wrong because then you can narrow
down the answers from four all the way to potentially two.
Also, I found that if you're not sure between two answers, the longer and more detailed ones are usually the correct ones, and if there is one outlier
answer that is completely different to the other three ones, that one is definitely wrong.
And that can be usually eliminated instantly.
So these were my key tips and tricks on how to become an academic weapon.
These tips honestly really were a game changer for me.
If you have a strategy that really works for you that I didn't mention, let me know down in the comments.
I would be super curious to know.
If you enjoyed this video, give it a like and subscribe, and I will see you next time.
Bye!